<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<refentry id="nullify">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>nullify</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>6</manvolnum>
    <refmiscinfo class="manual">Linux Games</refmiscinfo>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>nullify</refname>
    <refpurpose>Game of cards for Linux whose goal is to get rid all of your cards</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <cmdsynopsis>
      <command>nullify</command>
      <arg><option>options</option></arg>
    </cmdsynopsis>
    <refsect2>
      <title>OPTIONS</title>
      <para>Available options are:</para>
      <variablelist>                  
        <varlistentry>           
          <term>
            <option>-n --name=&lt;yourname&gt;</option>
          </term>        
          <listitem>                   
            <para>Set your name to something other than "Human"</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>                                      
            <option>-d --debug</option>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>It allows show the cards of the bots</para>
          </listitem>                                             
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>                                      
            <option>-f --skipframes=&lt;n&gt;</option>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Set the amount of frames to skip during animations.
             &lt;n&gt; must be an integer different than zero
            </para>
          </listitem>                                             
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>                                      
            <option>-t --total=&lt;n&gt;</option>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Specify play each game up to &lt;n&gt; points is to be reached
             (default = 16)
            </para>
          </listitem>                                             
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>                                      
            <option>-s --savelog</option>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Save the session log when the game exits (it must have been
             compiled with the --enable-xml-logs=yes option)
            </para>
          </listitem>                                             
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>                                      
            <option>-l --logfile=&lt;filename&gt;</option>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Save the session log to &lt;filename&gt; rather than to the
             default file "~/.nullify-session.xml"
            </para>
          </listitem>                                             
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>                                      
            <option>-R --replay-file=&lt;file&gt;</option>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Reproduce a saved game by reading it from XML &lt;file&gt;</para>
          </listitem>                                             
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>                                      
            <option>-H --replay-hand=&lt;g:h&gt;</option>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Reproduce the specified hand &lt;h&gt; of the game &lt;g&gt; only</para>
          </listitem>                                             
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>                                      
            <option>-L --list-hands=&lt;file&gt;</option>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Show available games and hands to replay from XML session &lt;file&gt; and exit</para>
          </listitem>                                             
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>                                      
            <option>-v --version</option>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Print the program version and exit</para>
          </listitem>                                             
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>                                      
            <option>-h --help</option>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Display this message</para>
          </listitem>                                             
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>                  
    </refsect2>
  </refsynopsisdiv>

  <refsect1>
    <title>DESCRIPTION</title>
    <para>
      Nullify is a cards game for Linux whose goal is to get rid of all of your cards.
      Each game is based on hands (formerly known as rounds) and each hand is based on
      turns. The hand ends when there is only one player who could not play all of the
      cards in its turns, with the number of them being added to its scores. The game
      ends when a player reaches the upper limit of scores allowed (default 16),
      becoming on the looser of the game.
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>MAIN RULE</title>
    <para>
      When in turn, the player must either play a card of the same kind / number as
      last card played or pick up one card from the deck. If is not possible play the
      new card because it mismatches kind or number, you must to do right-click over
      the deck and the turn is updated to the next player.
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>SPECIAL CARDS</title>
    <para>
      There are some cards with special meanings that modify either the amount of cards that
      you can play "in a single shot" or the amount of cards that you _must_ to get from
      the deck. The list is as follows:
      <variablelist>                  
        <varlistentry>           
          <term><option>Ace and two</option></term>        
          <listitem>                   
            <para>
              Each time a player dispatches an "A" or "2", the next player in turn will be
              forced to get up to 4 or 2 cards from the deck, respectively. As an exception
              to the rule, if the first card get is another "A" or "2" then the player can choose
              play that card, in which case the total sum of aces and two's played will be the
              amount of cards that the next player must get from the table.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>           
          <term><option>Four and seven</option></term>        
          <listitem>                   
            <para>
              Whether a "4" or "7" is played, another card of the same kind / number
              must be played.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>           
          <term><option>Jack</option></term>        
          <listitem>                   
            <para>
              Likewise, but also the player can select the kind of cards to play.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>           
          <term><option>Queen</option></term>        
          <listitem>                   
            <para>
              Whether a "Q" is played, the most immediate player in turn is skipped.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>           
          <term><option>King</option></term>
          <listitem>                   
            <para>
              Whether a "K" is played, the rotation mode is toggled clockwise/counter-clockwise.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>GETTING EXTRA POINTS</title>
    <para>
      You can collect extra points during each hand according to the amount of cards to get from
      the deck or the amount of cards dispatched in your turn. In fact, you will add 1 extra point
      for each 6 cards you pick up from the deck (e.g., which could be achieved if previous bots
      play aces and twos) and you will subtract 1 extra point for each 4 cards that you play
      sequentially in your turn (e.g., you can play a 4, then another 4, a 7 and then any arbitrary
      card matching the suit of the last 7).
    </para>
    <para>
      Since the maximum number of aces and twos that can be simultaneously played is 8, the
      maximum number of cards that you'd get from the deck would be 24 and, therefore, in that
      case you would add 4 special points. Similarly, due to the maximum number of cards that you
      can play sequentially in a turn is 17 (i.e., 4 x 4's + 4 x 7's + 4 x Jacks + 4 x Queens + 1),
      you would subtract 4 special points (-4).
    </para>
    <para>
      When the hand ends, all of these extra points are shown in the "Special" column of the
      Table of Scores. The "Total" column stores the total points accumulated in previous hands
      plus the number of cards which could not be played by the looser of the hand plus the
      special points for each player.
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>CONFIGURATION</title>
    <para>
     Nullify reads default game options from the system configuration file
     <filename>/usr/local/share/nullify/res/nullify.conf</filename>. This file contains
     one "keyword=value" pair per line, where "keyword" and its valid values are as
     it follows:
      <variablelist>                  
        <varlistentry>           
          <term><option>Player0</option></term>        
          <listitem>                   
            <para>
             Your name (defaults to "Human"). Only ASCII alphanumeric characters are
             currently supported. Also, the name will be truncated if its length is
             greater than or equal to 20.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>           
          <term><option>Player1</option></term>        
          <listitem>                   
            <para>
             Name of the first bot (the leftmost one). Constraints for Player0 name
             apply too.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>           
          <term><option>Player2</option></term>        
          <listitem>                   
            <para>
             Name of the second bot (the topmost one). Constraints for Player0 name
             apply too.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>           
          <term><option>Player3</option></term>        
          <listitem>                   
            <para>
             Name of the third bot (the rightmost one). Constraints for Player0 name
             apply too.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>           
          <term><option>Debug</option></term>        
          <listitem>                   
            <para>
             Set to 1 to show the cards of the bots. Possible values are 0 (default)
             and integers other than 0.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>           
          <term><option>SkipFrames</option></term>        
          <listitem>                   
            <para>
             Amount of non-rendered frames when either a player gets a card from
             the deck or plays one card to the stack. The lower this integer is, the
             slower will be the animations. Possible values are 1-MAX_INT, being 2
             the default value.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>           
          <term><option>Total</option></term>        
          <listitem>                   
            <para>
             Set the upper bound to be reached by any player, becoming itself on
             the looser of the current game and then start a new game. Default value
             is 16, which is best suited for the vast majority of games that I played.
             Keep in mind that set it to greater values can result on you spending
             too many of your precious hours, because after each hand some bots
             can add negative points to their scores.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>           
          <term><option>LogFilename</option></term>        
          <listitem>                   
            <para>
             Filename where to save the session log if "--savelog" option was
             provided on the command line and the game was compiled with XML support;
             otherwise, is ignored (defaults to "~/.nullify-session.xml").
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>                  
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>FILES</title>
    <variablelist>                  
      <varlistentry>           
        <term><filename>/usr/local/share/nullify/res/nullify.conf</filename></term>        
        <listitem>                   
          <para>
           Default settings read prior command line parsing is performed.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>                  
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>AUTHORS</title>
    <para>
      This manual page was written by Daniel Dwek <email>todovirtual15@gmail.com</email>.
    </para>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>
